Luiz Gonzaga dos Santos Filho, MBA

 ♥ Vancouver, Canada
 ♠ www.luiz.dev
 ➤ Email

in LinkedIn SpeakerDeck G GitHub

A brazillian-canadian people-first leader building impactful products and high-performing teams for ~21.5 years.

I grow people with empathy, trust and accountability and organizations of all sizes with efficient and low-touch processes.

I'm continually upskilling myself and love sharing what I know. Feel free to check some of my testimonials and recommendations on my LinkedIn and Topmate profiles.

For a more verbose version of my resumé, visit luiz.dev/cv/verbose.

Experience

🖫 Software Engineering Manager 🔿 Senior Software Engineering Manager @ Coursera

(S) Feb 2021 – present

- Cultivated talent: managed several teams and charters, hired promoted engineers to Senior, Staff and Manager
- Drove Enterprise growth: led key Enterprise initiatives and products, unlocking several millions of dollars in revenue yearly
- Enhanced organizational efficiency: conceptualized, implemented and improved several team and org-wide processes, resulting in improved metrics and accountability, reduced touchpoints and better-informed leadership decision-making
- Championed DE&I and well-being: authored and drove different org-wide policies around DE&I, measurably increased our hiring pipeline's diversity and maintained highest team retention in the org

🖫 Software Engineering Manager II 🔿 Software Engineering Manager III @ Amazon / AWS

(Sep 2017 - Dec 2020

- At Amazon Payments: led a cross-functional team to deliver the end-to-end payments integration for Amazon Turkey (amazon.com.tr), involving international and cross-department collaboration and materializing Amazon's expansion in Europe; drove early adoption of PSD2 regulations, ensuring European market compliance ahead of competitors; owned Payment on Delivery for India market
- At AWS Route53: hired and grew a team from scratch; measurably improved operational efficiency, accessibility, and usability across five different products; owned multiple product roadmaps and delivered two global product launches, expanding AWS Route53's presence into new markets and regions
- Drove organizational change and fostered inclusion: improved our sourcing efficiency by ~32% and our pipeline's diversity by ~11%; championed an engineering-wide policy to promote inclusion and belonging; as a certified Cultural Competences for Teams instructor, trained hundreds of leaders and engineers around diversity and inclusion
- Mentored and supported other managers: served on the Software Engineering Manager Peer Advisory board, providing guidance and support to peers

Senior Frontend Engineer → Frontend Team Lead @ Brandwatch

Apr 2016 – Feb 2017

- As the Frontend team lead: helped the PM with agile ceremonies and backlog prioritization; liaison with the team manager in the UK
- As a Senior Frontend Engineer: worked existing and new feature development on Brandwatch's main product (Analytics); refactored thousands of files on a 5-year-old jQuery codebase, improving bundle size, patching security vulnerabilities, and enabling new features to be used

Full-stack engineer @ X-Team

Apr 2015 – Apr 2015

 Short collaboration with X-Team's CTO researching, planning and developing the next phase of X-Labs (their open source initiative) and other internal projects involving IndexedDB

Software Engineering Manager @ DataEasy

(Jun 2014 – Mar 2016

- Led Engineering Transformation: directed a company-wide shift to modern DevOps and ChatOps practices, including Git, SemVer, CI pipelines, live application monitoring, automated release management, enabling higher quality and faster releases and allowing the IT department to stay leaner
- Championed Process Improvement: mapped all engineering processes, reduced touchpoints and staffing needs
- Fostered growth and upskilling: partnered with a local university to provide automated testing courses for senior engineers, streamlining testing cycles and reducing release bottlenecks
- Cultivated Innovation and Learning: created a bi-weekly program fostering innovation and knowledge sharing through tech talks and experimentation with new technologies

Senior Frontend Engineer @ Brandwatch

Apr 2013 – Nov 2013

Developed their main product line: brand Analytics

Wrote codemods to refactor thousands of merge	of files, defining conventions for all frontend, red	ucing code review length and improving time to
Senior Frontend Engineer → Frontend Team Lead @ Content Fleet		() Apr 2012 – Mar 2013
optimization initiatives, significantly redu	ST APIs and core MVC applications. Led mobile cing network calls and minimizing source code frontend strategy, conventions, quality, performan	·
Full-stack Engineer @ Goiás State Government		Sev 2007 – Mar 2012
 Worked as a full-stack engineer on the Cover 200k people Led several performance, usability and a 		M) system, supporting payroll and other features for
Junior Full-stack Engineer @ DR Sistema	as & Interagi	() 2004 – 2005
 At Interagi, I developed CRUD application At DR Sistemas, I developed a Backend 	ons and did some programmatic image processi I application for the public law sector	ng
Misc Software Engineering & Consultancy gigs @ Freelancer		Jan 2003 – Dec 2014
 SENAC Goiás, Goiânia, Brazil — Consu of dynamic versus compiled languages. 	ultancy on migrating a desktop application to a valtancy on web development, best practices, proment of the Public contest (Vestibular) system ar	ductivity tools, agile methodologies and comparison
Other		
Over 23 experiences as an instructor or speake of them at <u>luiz.dev/cv/verbose</u> .	r and 7 volunteer positions around leadership, w	veb development, community and the arts. See all
Education		
Business Process Management, MBA Trianglement Institute (IGTI) – Brazil	Computer Engineering, Bachelor Federal University of Goiás – Brazil Extra studies on Software Engineering Relative average grade: 85%	Computer Science, Visiting Student Saint Mary's University – Canada i Emerging Leaders of America Scholarship 2nd round on Trumped Competition
Languages		
Portuguese — Native	English — Fluent	▲☑ German & Spanish — Basic
Other		
Over 32 courses and specializations taken, 70 bleadership and self growth. See all of them at <u>lu</u>		nents on software engineering, entrepreneurship,
Skills Overall skills along my career in alphabetical order		
community continuous integration cross-functional collaborate education effective communication enterprise event mana internal communication jasmine java ee javascript jenki monitoring mustache mysql new relic ngo node new phantom php pivotal tracker policy development postmupublic speaking react remote collaboration require require software development life cycle software engineering software	gement external communication (flux (freetest (github) (go ns) (jira) (jquery) (jsp) (kanban) (leadership) (leveldb) (man on-for profit) (operational efficiency) (organizational strategy) particular process (process improvement) (product development) (profit (pr	anagement devops docker documentation ed-tech pogle apps scripts (hibernate highcharts hiring html) nagement marketing maven mentoring mongodb ayment services (people management) (performance metrics) product launch (project management) (public relations) ute 53 (scrum (semver) (shell script) (software development)